<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd in the cathedral of Lincoln, August 1, 1680 (being the assize Sunday) by Tho. Hindmarsh ...</title>
            <author>Hindmarsh, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43855</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2063A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40988</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19542185</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19542185</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109098</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43855)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109098)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1689:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd in the cathedral of Lincoln, August 1, 1680 (being the assize Sunday) by Tho. Hindmarsh ...</title>
                  <author>Hindmarsh, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Joseph Hindmarsh ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts XXIV, 25 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109098:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd in the CATHEDRAL OF LINCOLN, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1. 1680.</p>
            <p>(Being the ASSIZE Sunday.)</p>
            <p>By THO. HINDMARSH A.M. and Vicar of <hi>Long Ourisby</hi> in <hi>Lincolnſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Joſeph Hindmarſh</hi> at the <hi>Black Bull</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:109098:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109098:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable and Truly Vertuous THE Lady <hi>ELIZABETH,</hi> Counteſs Dowager of <hi>Strafford.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe many and great Favours which I have received from you, exceeding all poſſibility of requital; have left me nothing to betake my ſelf to but an ingenious acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Neither could I think but that a private acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment was too mean an expreſſion, either of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my Obligations, or the gratitude of my own mind. I have therefore prefixed your name to the following Diſcourſe; not from any flattering Opinion, as if it could merit this honour, but that I may by theſe preſents mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to the World in what ſtrict, ſolemn, but yet pleaſing bonds, I am for ever tied, and devoted to your Family. Your own Vertues being very perſpicuous both in your Proſperous and Adverſe condition, hath produced in all generous and loyal ſouls the higheſt eſteem and venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for you: ſo that I need not mention your near Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to that great Example of Excellency and Fatality, your deareſt Lord. If I ſhould ſtretch out this Epiſtle into a large Panegyrick, I need not fear the injuries of
<pb facs="tcp:109098:3"/>Truth, (the Subject being as far from flattery, as the neceſſity of it) but yet it is not unlikely that I ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe you: for all Perſons of your Honour and Merit account it an Aſſault upon their Modeſty to hear them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves applauded: and I am confident that you are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pleaſed with Meriting, than Hearing your own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations. I ſhall therefore wave that, and betake my ſelf to this, which is more agreeable to my Profeſſion, and more acceptable to You; and that is, to beg of God that he would ſtill continue to crown you with the Bleſſings of this Life, till he receive you to a better; which is the hearty Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Hounours Moſt humble and faithful Servant and Chaplain THO. HINDMARSH.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109098:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>ACTS xxiv. <hi>V.</hi> 25. the former part.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And as he reaſoned of righteouſneſs, temperance, and judgment to come,</hi> Felix <hi>trembled.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IF Accuſations might be thought ſufficient to render men criminal, and if all the aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and calumnies which foul-mouthed Envy can invent and diſperſe, might be taken for the words of Truth and Soberneſs, then indeed Chriſtianity would be made the moſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilential Doctrine, and the Profeſſors of it the greateſt Villains in the World. For ſuch is the buſie and indefatigable nature of that irreconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able enemy of Mankind, <hi>Satan,</hi> as to be always ſending forth his Emiſſaries and Agents for the beſpattering of that Innocency which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not corrupt: and they retain ſtifly that Leſſon which one of his apteſt Scholars firſt learned and broached, the <hi>Florentine Machiavel,</hi> that if they do but calumniate ſtrongly, and throw dirt with both hands, they may be ſure that ſome of it will ſtick. It is no wonder then that the poor Church of <hi>England</hi> ſhould at this day be loaded with a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:109098:4"/>contrariety of ſlanderous reproaches, and have ſuch imputations faſtned upon her, as are incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with, and repugnant to each other. Her Enemies abroad ſhall accuſe her of Novelty, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticiſm, Schiſm, and Hereſie, and all thoſe hard names which may affright the Vulgar: and her Back-friends at home ſhall impeach her of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, as if ſhe was now the next door to <hi>Rome,</hi> and juſt going to throw her ſelf into the arms of that <hi>Step-Mother,</hi> who by an unnatural ferity and not fondneſs, would ſqueeze her to death. Her Orthodox and Regular Clergy have been boldly aſperſed by<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>A Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Pamphlet entituled,</hi> A Letter from a Perſon of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to a Friend in the Country.</note> ſome as the <hi>Soothers</hi> of their Prince; and again they are repreſented by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as the <hi>Flatterers</hi> of the People. Sometimes we are drawn as the great <hi>Buoyers up of Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Government,</hi> as if we, of all others were ſuch creeping Fools as to be ambitious of Slavery: and then again with another daſh the Picture is quite altered, and ſo we are taken to be ſuch <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtors as Cajole the Multitude.</hi> Such a Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty does this Body of our Church bear to its myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Head Chriſt Jeſus, that as in many other things, ſo in this alſo, ſhe like him, hath been cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified betwixt two Thieves. Here indeed is our comfort, that we have no worſe treatment than our great Lord had;<note place="margin">Mat. 10.25.</note> 
               <hi>And if they called the Maſter of the Houſe</hi> Beelzebub, <hi>what language may the Servants of the Family expect?</hi> He, although he was rightly
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:109098:4"/>ſtiled <hi>the Prince of Peace,</hi> yet was he vehemently accuſed as <hi>a mover of Sedition.</hi> He, who in the caſe of Tribute gave <hi>Caeſar</hi> his utmoſt due, yet was he highly clamoured againſt as <hi>no Friend to Caeſar.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 19.12.</note> And as he, ſo his Apoſtles alſo were trailed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Tribunals as the greateſt Criminals. To in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in none but our Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul,</hi> you find him here in this Chapter called before <hi>a Tribunal,</hi> and a pert Orator <hi>Tertullus</hi> ſtarted out againſt him, who with a great deal of vehemency and malignity of Spirit, calls him <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>a peſtilent Fellow, a mover of Sedition among all the Jews throughout the World, and a Ring-leader of the Sect of the Nazarens.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>v.</hi> 10. is admitted to ſpeak in his own defence; who not retorting the foul lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage which his adverſary was maſter of, with a great deal of modeſty and ingenuity wipes off the main body of their charge, only confeſſing that innocent part of it, that after the way which they call <hi>Hereſie, ſo worſhipped he the God of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers:</hi> this ſets him right in the opinion of his Judge, and he is likely now to have a fair Trial. In the interim (till <hi>Lycias</hi> the chief Captain came, who was a principal witneſs in the caſe) the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour <hi>Felix</hi> ſends for <hi>Paul,</hi> that he might preach to him concerning the <hi>Faith in Chriſt.</hi> And you have here in my Text, the Grounds and Heads of S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Diſcourſe, with the effect and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent of it: <hi>For as he reaſoned of righteouſneſs, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance and judgment to come,</hi> Felix <hi>trembled.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:109098:5"/>
            <p>In which words be pleaſed to obſerve with me theſe three particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, The Subject or Matter of S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe; and that contains theſe three things, <hi>Righteouſneſs, Temperance, and Judgment to come.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, The Manner of the Apoſtles hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them; and that is expreſſed in this Phraſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, by a way of Reaſoning.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, The Influence which his Diſcourſe had upon his great Auditor; <hi>It made him tremble. For when he reaſoned,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <p>I begin with the firſt:</p>
            <p n="1">I. The Subject or Ground-work of S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Diſcourſe, and that you ſee contains theſe three things, <hi>Righteouſneſs, Temperance, and Judgment to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Of <hi>Righteouſneſs:</hi> The word in the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and is of ſo large a ſignification as to comprehend the whole Moral Law, the Duties of the firſt and ſecond Table. The word <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> or <hi>Juſtice,</hi> is, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> defines it, <hi>ſuum cuique tribuere,</hi> to give every one his due; <hi>ſuum Deo</hi> firſt, and then <hi>ſuum proximo;</hi> to give God his due, and then your Neighbour alſo. Firſt the word Righteouſneſs, as it relates to God, does contain all that religious worſhip which we owe unto him; it comprehends the dedication of our ſouls and bodies to his ſervice, it involves ſuch a fixing of our thoughts and affections upon that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109098:5"/>all-ſufficient being, as with a pleaſing violence will conſtrain us to love him, even with all our heart, and with all our ſoul, and all our mind. And can there be a greater piece of Righteouſneſs than to pay all our ſervices to him, who gave us all we have? Can any thing be more juſt and equitable than that we ſhould pay our hearty thanks for that which we can never requite? Do we allow our earthly Parents an ingenuous ſubmiſſion, and humble obſervance, and ſhall we be peeviſh and perverſe, ſtubborn and refractory to the Father of Spirits? 'Tis the unavoidable conſequence of this argument, and the perpetual regret which wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men find in their conſciences for not comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with it, that hath made them endeavour all they can to perſuade themſelves to be Atheiſts; and therefore they have taken up a new and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſale way of diſcharging their obligations, by the bold denial of that Deity, to whom they ſhould pay them. Not but that I am very confident their hearts give their tongues the Lie; and they are onely got to a cold Wiſh, but can never arrive to a warm Belief, <hi>there is no God.</hi> For we may have ſeen ſome Children that have been ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracious, as to refuſe to give the honour due unto a Parent, but there was never any ſo irrational as to deny they had a Father.</p>
            <p>But yet ſuch is the impudence and folly of the Age we live in, as to ſay, and defend any thing:
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109098:6"/>to fanſie our ſelves to have ſprung up like a <hi>Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> or <hi>Muſhrome,</hi> rather than believe we had our original from an Infinite Wiſdom and Power, the Characters of which are ſo very legible in our Faces, and yet much more in our Souls. But it is not with ſuch men that I deſign to argue (if there were any ſuch here) becauſe, in truth, they ought to be looked upon as perſons out of their<note n="*" place="margin">Eſſe Deos qui negat, vix eum ſanae men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis exiſtimem. <hi>Tul. nat. deor. l. 2.</hi>
               </note> wits: but I would rather apply my ſelf to all thoſe that are well backt with power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that by a moſt ſtrict and impartial execution of the Laws, thoſe Contemners of Religion may be bridled and corrected: and that men ſhould be as fearful to burleſque the Scriptures, and blaſpheme God, as they are to ſpeak and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the blackeſt Treaſon againſt their Prince.</p>
            <p>I confeſs it might do well if they could be trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as the Law hath provided for, and as indeed they are, mad men, if they could be ordered to a <hi>Dark Lodging</hi> and <hi>Coarſe Diet;</hi> for that would be the moſt effectual means to the reducing of them to a ſobriety of mind, as well as of body. And as for us who are fully convinced, that the profeſſion of our Faith in God, and the acknowledgment of our dependance on him, are things highly rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, and indiſpenſably neceſſary; ſo let us chearfully and faithfully continue in them: and ſeeing it is impoſſible for any to argue, let them never laugh us into Infidelity. Let our care be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109098:6"/>in all our devotions to mix an inward ſincerity with an outward gravity, that nothing undecent and unbecoming may be ſeen in us by God or Man. As we would abhor the ſight of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digy, a <hi>Speculative Atheiſt,</hi> ſo let not us make our ſelves a greater, by being <hi>Practical</hi> ones. And if by continuance in this courſe, we do not find our ſelves defaultive in this<note n="*" place="margin">Sublata pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, &amp; ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas humani ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris, &amp; una excellentiſſima virtus juſtitia tollitur. <hi>Tull. nat. deor. l. 1.</hi>
               </note> righteouſneſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, then we may be confident there will be ſeen in us the fruits of that righteouſneſs which is due to our Neighbour: and that is the</p>
            <p>Second thing contained in this phraſe of my Text, his <hi>reaſoning of righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is this Juſtice or Righteouſneſs which is commonly called a Cardinal Vertue; for as the Door leans and turns upon the Hinges, ſo the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire carriage and deportment of our whole life betwixt us and our Neighbour ſhould be born up and backed by the bands of Juſtice. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever comes within the compaſs of that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>(as S. <hi>James</hi> calls it) the <hi>Royal Law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">James 2.8</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf;</hi> even all the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and inſtances of duty between man and man, they are all compriſed in this long word, but larger virtue, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. In this is compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended reverence and obedience to our Superiors, curteſie and humanity to our Equals, kindneſs and condeſcention to our Inferiors, with juſtice and upright dealing towards all.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:109098:7"/>
            <p>It might do well, if ſome would conſider it, how great a ſhare of Juſtice is contained in pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an high reverence to the Perſons, and a ſtrict obedience to the well contrived Laws of their Governors. I am ſure they are very forgetful of their duty, and themſelves, who beſpatter the Government with moſt virulent Libels, and are not afraid (with thoſe filthy Dreamers S. <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeaks of) <hi>to deſpiſe Dominion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. 8.</note> 
               <hi>and ſpeak evil of Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities.</hi> And Superiors too, although they need not be taught, yet they may be modeſtly put in mind how much Juſtice becomes them, and that their Robes never look ſo gloriouſly and ſplendidly as when they are lined with Juſtice. If Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Judgment are the habitation of Gods Throne, and Juſtice be ſaid to ſtand faſt by his Judgment Seat; then certainly thoſe that are ſtiled <hi>gods</hi> need not be aſhamed to have them ſit upon the Seat of Judicature with them.<note place="margin">Pſal. 82.6.</note> It was a ſmart reply of the old Woman to a great Prince, who, when he told her <hi>he was not at leiſure to do her Juſtice,</hi> returned, <hi>Why then are you at leiſure to be a King?</hi> Away with thoſe Paraſites that would flatter their Prince to believe this to be a piece of as good Divinity as it is Poetry, <q>—ſtat pro ratione voluntas.</q> You ſhall never find any, except the fool-hardy <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> that would make his Prince a <hi>Leviathan;</hi> exempt him clearly from the eternal Laws of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109098:7"/>God and Nature,<note place="margin">V. Hobs Lev.</note> and give him leave to legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate the greateſt Villanies, and make the <hi>Alcoran</hi> Canonical if he pleaſes. No, no; S. <hi>Paul</hi> reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of righteouſneſs to this great <hi>Felix,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he was the Husband of three Queens, as <hi>Suetonius</hi> tells us, and the Governour of <hi>Judaea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Suet. in Claud. vit. 28.</note> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> aſſures us. And I am very much inclined to believe that S. <hi>Paul</hi> preached on ſuch a Subject, upon the account of its appoſiteneſs and fitneſs to the condition of his Auditor. He had heard, without doubt, by the publick voice of Fame, or ſome other way, that he had made his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment infamous by Tyranny and Cruelty; and therefore he fairly lays before him, how neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it was for one of his quality to be clothed with Juſtice, and leaves his own guilty conſcience to make the application. And that you may not fanſie this to be a fond conjecture of mine, be pleaſed to take the cenſure which that weighty Hiſtorian <hi>Tacitus</hi> gives you of him.<note n="*" place="margin">Antonius Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix per omnem ſevitiam ac li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidinem jus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium ſervili ingenio exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult. <hi>Corn. Tacit. Hiſt. 5. V. 26.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Antonius Felix</hi> being of a ſordid nature, did abuſe his truſt of Government with all kind of licentiouſneſs and cruelty: yea his low and mercenary diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition may ſafely be concluded from the Verſe which follows my Text, where S. <hi>Luke</hi> tells us he expected a Bribe from <hi>Paul,</hi> and hoped that ſome money ſhould have been given him to ſet him free. This was a baſe unworthy thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, to make Juſtice mercenary, which can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109098:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:109098:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:109098:9"/>be undervalude ſo much, as when in this manneroit hath apnice ſet on it.</p>
            <p>And as this Vertue extends it ſelf to Superiors and Inferiors, ſo likewiſe muſt it have a great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence amongſt thoſe that are Equals. What is it that diſtinguiſhes a Society of Men, from a Herd of wild Beaſts? Is it not the greedy ſnatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and rapacious devouring of the latter? And is it not the fair and mild, the juſt and generous dealing of the former? If we once come to ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie that old Adage, <hi>Homo homini Lupus,</hi> One man is a Wolf to another, we ſhould leave nothing to be diſtinguiſhed by, but the outward appearance and countenance; whereas thoſe that live mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually within the bounds of Juſtice, O how peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and ſafe is their condition? how free are they from noiſe and tumult? how much exempt from all fears of diſturbance? Yea there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more calm and quiet than their outward condition, except it be the inward ſtate and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of their mind. How eaſily can the juſt man obtain his ends, ſeeing nothing extravagant and unhanſom is contained in them? For as it is an infallible rule in Geometry, that of all Lines or Surfaces contained within the ſame bounds, the ſtreight line, and the plain ſurface are the ſhorteſt; ſo is it alſo in morality: for by the right line of Juſtice upon the plain ground of Vertue, a man will ſooneſt arrive to any well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choſen
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:109098:9"/>end.<note place="margin">V.D. <hi>Barrows</hi> Serm on Prov. 10.9.</note> To clamber (as a learned man ſays) over the Fences of Duty, to break through Hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Right, to treſpaſs upon hallowed Inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, may ſeem the moſt ſhort and compendious ways of getting thither where one would be: but doth not a man venture breaking his neck, or ſcratching his face, incurring the greateſt miſchief and trouble thereby? But thus much for the firſt Vertue which S. <hi>Paul</hi> diſcourſed to <hi>Felix,</hi> when he reaſoned of righteouſneſs; which contained our duty to God, and our Neighbour alſo. I paſs on to the Second, and that is <hi>Temperance;</hi> or if you take it from the Fountain <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Now although the original of the word may argue it a Maſculine, yet methinks it may not improperly be ſtiled a Maiden Vertue, becauſe it keeps the Soul clean and tight. The word con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains in it theſe two things, <hi>Sobriety</hi> and <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt <hi>Sobriety:</hi> This is the Vertue which bears up and contains a man within the grandeur of his own ſpecies. If he once falls beſides this, he then drops into a confederacy with Brutes; yea, can ſcarce be thought a ſit companion for them. They indeed only gratifie the longings of Nature, but he can never be ſatisfied unleſs you drown him. How unfit is anintemperate man to be admitted as a ſure Friend, or a faithful Confident, when he is ſo ready to pour outall his ſecrets with his ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetings
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109098:10"/>into his next mans boſom? How unqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified is he for any imployment? He is either too idle, or too buſie; too light, or too heavy. And what way ſhall he take to find out any thing, who in the firſt place hath loſt himſelf? But he that keeps himſelf abſtemious and ſober, hath his Wits about him, and his reaſon clear, and is in a good capacity to manage his own or the publick buſineſs, without being obnoxious to thoſe affronts and injuries which Intemperance would expoſe him to: at the leaſt he may keep a ſafe guard upon his own body, and ſo beat off all undecent onſets and aſſaults that would vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late his <hi>Chaſtity.</hi> And that is the ſecond thing contained in the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Now the lovelineſs of this Vertue can no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter appear, than by comparing it with the Defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of the contrary Vice. The odiouſneſs of which may in ſome meaſure be collected, by that regret and checking which it puts upon the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of men in their firſt violations of Chaſtity, How often are they put to the bluſh, before they can arrive to an impudence in ſin? How fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully do they ſtand trembling between guilt and horror, and are at length forced to ruſh into the darkeſt corners, as being the fitteſt places for the works of darkneſs? I confeſs indeed, the immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty of our Times hath almoſt broke the force of this argument; for our Gallants are got to that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109098:10"/>height of Impiety, as you ſhall hear them glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in nothing but their ſhame. Modeſty is now looked upon as a childiſh and ungentile quality; but he is the man of ſpirit and breeding, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights to wallow like a Beaſt in the groſſeſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality. Good God! How far are they ſunk below the nature of men that can boaſt of their ſins of that kind, as of their ſpecial excellency? When, if that be the meaſure, a libidinous Goat muſt confeſledly be eſteemed the more excellent Creature.</p>
            <p>But let us look back a little from our Times, and ſee how the caſe ſtood when <hi>Felix</hi> was Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour. We may very much fear, that <hi>Felix</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was highly guilty of the breach of tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: and I am more than half perſuaded, that S. <hi>Paul</hi> pickt out theſe two Vertues, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Temperance, to diſcourſe unto him, that he might ſeriouſly lay to heart how ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully he had prevaricated both in one and the other. For as before we repreſented him to you as one unacquainted with Juſtice, ſo now he ſhall appear as great a ſtranger to Temperance: His Wife <hi>Druſilla,</hi> was as great in birth, as ſhe was infamous in life. She was the Niece of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony</hi> and <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> ſays <hi>Tacitus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tac. Hiſt. 5.</note> the daughter of <hi>Herod</hi> the Great, the ſiſter of <hi>Agrippa</hi> junior, but a moſt laſcivious woman:<note place="margin">Vid. Groc. in loc.</note> who having forſaken the princely bed of her own Husband, followed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109098:11"/>her Gallant <hi>Felix,</hi> with whoſe love and beauty being taken, ſhe was at length married to him. Such were the guilty Auditors of our Apoſtles Sermon, and as we may ſuppoſe, he reaſoned to them of the excellency of theſe two Virtues, Righteouſneſs and Temperance, and might with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, ſhew them the great ſhame that even in this life would follow ſuch practices as they took; ſo we are ſure he preſſed them home with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections of a future ſtate, and called to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance that there was a Judgment to come. Which is the.</p>
            <p>Third and laſt thing in the Subject of S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Diſcourſe; <hi>For he reaſoned to them of righteouſneſs, temperance, and judgment to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here alſo I ſhall briefly conſider two things, the Certainty, and Terribleneſs of that fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Judgment: the Certainty of the thing it ſelf, and the Terribleneſs of its circumſtances. Firſt for its certainty: And this may be cleared either from the conſideration of our own, or the divine nature, from the contemplation of our ſelves who are to be ſubjected to it, or of that God who is to execute it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If we contemplate our ſelves, the very frame and conſtitution of our natures have the Idaea's of Immortality, and a future exiſtency ſtamped upon them. You have the general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and approbation of mankind in all ages and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109098:11"/>places of the World to countenance and confirm this truth. It is not a new invention, nor an up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtart notion of yeſterday; but claims an acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with Mankind, even from his firſt Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal; and hath through all viciſſitudes ſtuck ſo cloſe to him, that we may ſafely conclude it will never leave him to the end of the World. Let our Navigators ſail either to the Eaſt or Weſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, let them make their Voyages either to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the North or South Poles, yet amongſt all that variety of Faces, Cuſtoms, Religions, and Tempers, every one kept the notion of a future Being, and that their actions were to be rewarded or puniſhed when they went from hence. The cold <hi>Ruſsian</hi> keeps this truth wrapt up in his warm Furs, and the ſcorched <hi>Moor</hi> ſees it almoſt as plain and naked as his own body. Yea, it is the obſervation of <hi>Plmy.</hi> that thoſe barbarous people that have neither Cloths to cover their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs, nor Laws for a common ſecurity, that live by the rules of ferity and luſt; and differ from the Beaſts ſeemingly, in little elſe but exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſhape; that have neither Towns nor Houſes, and but juſt reaſon enough to provide for the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of Nature; yet theſe live in expectation and belief of a life after this. Now if this was not a moſt certain truth grounded upon princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples obvious to all, what reaſon could we give of ſo univerſal a conſent? How can it be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109098:12"/>that all men ſhould conſpire to deceive themſelves and their innocent poſterity? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it may well be thought to be the firſt-born of abſurdities to think that thoſe who are at ſo vaſt a diſtance in place and nature, and all other circumſtances, ſhould agree in a common deceit, and jump in the ſame impoſture? For how ſhould all the World conſpire in a Lie? How come the beſt of men to have earneſt deſires and longings after a future ſtate? and how come the worſt of men to be horribly afraid of it? What is the meaning of that ſtrong averſion which all conſiderate men have againſt a dark ſtate of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilation? What is the matter that Reaſon can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not think of it without great regret of mind? How comes it to paſs that there is a natural de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire in all men after a ſtate of happineſs and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection? It is generally agreed that no natural deſire is in vain: all other things have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to ſatisfie their natural appetites.<note n="*" place="margin">Princip. of Nat. Relig. by the L. B. of <hi>Cheſter.</hi>
               </note> And if we conſider the utter impoſſibility of attaining to any ſuch condition in this life, this will render it highly credible that there muſt be another ſtate wherein this happineſs is attainable; otherwiſe mankind muſt fail of his chief end, being by a natural principle moſt ſtrongly inclined to ſuch a ſtate of happineſs as he can never attain to. As if he were purpoſely framed to be tormented between theſe two Paſſions, Deſire and Deſpair;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:109098:12"/>an earneſt propenſion after happineſs, and an ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter incapacity of ever enjoying it. As if Nature it ſelf, whereby all other things are diſpoſed to their perfection, did ſerve only in mankind to make them miſerable. And which is yet more conſiderable, the better and the wiſer any man is, the more earneſt deſires and hopes hath he after ſuch a ſtate of happineſs. So that if there be no ſuch thing as a future exiſtence, not onely Nature but Vertue likewiſe muſt contribute to make men miſerable: which is a conſequence ſo groſly unreaſonable as not to be ſwallowed.</p>
            <p>And how comes it to paſs that wicked men alſo cannot throw away thoſe notions which they would ſo gladly be ſhut of? What is the meaning that among the jollities of this life, they are irreſiſtibly put in mind of being called to a reckoning in another? When their actions are ſo ſecret that they cannot be diſcerned, and their perſons ſo powerful that they cannot be puniſhed by an earthly tribunal, How come they then to be ſeized with the horrours of an all-diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning and all-controlling Judicature? What ſhall we think of it, when thoſe-who have made it their buſineſs to root out of the minds of men all ſuch troubleſom notions about a future ſtate ſhould yet be the perſons who are moſt aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hi ſunt qui trepidant &amp; ad omnia fulgura pallent.</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:109098:13"/>Theſe are they that ſhake and tremble at their own thoughts; and if they do but hear a clap of Thunder, they imagine that voice is calling them to a Judgment to come. But to proceed:</p>
            <p>Secondly, The conſideration of Gods Nature, as well as our own, will abundantly prove a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Judgment. For when we think upon the Divine Nature, we muſt look upon him as clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with an attribute of inflexible and unaltera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Juſtice. His Juſtice is ſo eſſential to his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, that we may as well deny him to be God as to be Juſt. We may therefore infallibly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude <hi>that God is a moſt juſt Judge:</hi> and if he be ſo, we may as ſafely conclude, that after this life he will judge the World in righteouſneſs. For as the affairs of this preſent World are ordered, though they lie under the diſpoſition of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, yet they ſhew no ſign of an univerſal Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. The divine diſpenſations in this life, are many times promiſcuous and uncertain; ſo that a man cannot judge of love or hatred,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.1.</note> by all that is before him. The worſt of men are ſometimes in the beſt condition: and the beſt men may ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally take up thoſe words of S. <hi>Paul, If in this life onley we had hope,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.19.</note> 
               <hi>we ſhould be of all men moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable.</hi> The proud Tyrant doth lift up his head againſt Heaven and yet proſpers; when the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout ſoul may lift up his hands thither, and yet be undone. So that nothing is more certain
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:109098:13"/>than that in this life, Rewards are not correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the Vertues, nor Puniſhments proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to the ſins of men. Which conſideration muſt needs make us infer a future ſtate, and day of accounts; and then we ſhall be forced to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge in the words of the Pſalmiſt, that <hi>Verily there is a reward for the righteous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 58.11.</note> 
               <hi>doubtleſs there is a God that judgeth the earth.</hi> Thus the belief of a Judgment-day, is not (you ſee) a Panick fear or melancholy dream. It is no trick of Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians or <hi>Mormo</hi> of Prieſts to fright Fools and keep the World in awe: but brings ſuch reaſons and conſiderations for its reception, as may make us conclude it to be unqueſtionably certain. And as we have conſidered the Certainty of the thing it ſelf, ſo in the next place, let us not forget the Terribleneſs of its circumſtances.</p>
            <p>As to theſe indeed we are altogether beholden to Divine Revelation. For although the light of Nature can inform us in general that there will be a Day of Judgment, and we may ſurely look for it: yet it is not able to conjecture what ſhall be the Solemnities of that time, nor with what pomp and majeſty the Judge ſhall appear. It is true, the Holy Ghoſt hath drawn the tranſactions of this day in lively colours; and they are laid before us, under the reſemblance of a formal Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciary Proceſs. The Books are ſaid to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, the Judge is placed upon his Throne, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:109098:14"/>all the Sons of men that ever lived upon the Earth, ſtand liſtning to hear their Sentence at that dreadful Bar. And ſeeing <hi>at our Lords coming the powers of Heaven ſhall be</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 24.29. <hi>Orig.</hi> and <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſl.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſhaken,</hi> that is, (as ſome learned Fathers interpret) the Angels them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (though pure and innocent Creatures) ſhall quake and tremble. What conſternation ſhall ſeize upon the ſpirits of men, who know themſelves to be loaded with ſin and duſt? O how paſſionately and differently will mankind be concerned at that time! What tranſports of Joy, what raptures of Bliſs ſhall be read in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances of Gods Children, when as the faces of the wicked ſhall gather blackneſs; and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction of their eyes, and ſhivering of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, will ſet forth thoſe diſmal agonies their ſouls are in. The jovial Drunkard ſhall then drop the ſparkling Glaſs out of his fingers, and will find that his great draughts here, will highly inflame both his reckoning and his thirſt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. The ſpruce Lover ſhall then exchange his languiſhing for a more tormenting kind of unquenchable flame. The profeſt Worldling will (like a profuſe Prodigal) be throwing away his beloved Bags: for alas! he knows they will not be taken there as good ſecurity. The merry Droll and ſcoffer at Religion, will then be quite put out of tune as well as countenance. The bold and daring Atheiſt ſhall then ſtandſneaking
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:109098:14"/>and trembling; and be horribly aſtoniſhed at the ſight of his former folly, and approaching miſery: <hi>But as for the righteous, it ſhall not be ſo with them.</hi> It will be their day of feſtivity and triumph, for <hi>they ſhall be called forth to the marriage-ſupper of the Lamb.</hi> The juſt man then ſhall live by his faith, and the bountiful man ſhall find the rewards of his charity: the temperate perſon ſhall drink of the Rivers of bliſs, and the chaſte ſoul ſhall be ſwallowed up in the arms of infinite love. Theſe, or ſuch as theſe, will be the various circumſtances which will crown the ſolemnity of the laſt Judgment. Happy are we if either the lovelineſs of the one, or the affrightfulneſs of the other, can prevail with us to make up our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts againſt that day. And thus much may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for the firſt particular, having conſidered the ſubject, or matter of S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Diſcourſe, as it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in it theſe three things, <hi>Righteouſneſs, Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and Judgment to come;</hi> I paſs on now to the Second particular, which is, to conſider the manner of the Apoſtles handling them, and that is expreſſed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by a way of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning.</p>
            <p>There are two ſorts of men that are for far dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent ways of preaching from this which S. <hi>Paul</hi> uſed. If they had been to make a Proſelyte of <hi>Felix,</hi> Oh! they would never have done it by the carnal way of reaſon. The two extreams that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:109098:15"/>I mean, are the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> on one ſide, and the <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> on the other. Thoſe would force you to be Chriſtians by the ſevere methods of violence and cruelty; and theſe would lead you by the Dark-Lanthern of the Spirit into a Fools Paradice, taking all the Whimſies of their own Brains for Divine Illuminations. We will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider each of them a little, and then we ſhall bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſee the difference from that method which S. <hi>Paul</hi> took. It cannot be denied but the <hi>Romiſh</hi> contrivance is very ſtrong and powerful; but then here is the fault of it, they are ſo extreamly bent upon the making of us Chriſtians, as that they quite forget we are ſo much as Men. It was this method which the <hi>Spaniards</hi> uſed in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the poor <hi>Indians,</hi> when they hold Water in the one hand, and a Dagger in the other; put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them to their choice of the two Baptiſms, the one of Water, and the other of Blood. Thus <hi>Henry</hi> III. thought to fright the Young Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> out of his Religion, by that equally ſharp &amp; ſhort way of argument, containing but theſe three words,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Davila</hi>'s Hiſt. Civ. Wars of <hi>France.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Maſs, Death,</hi> or <hi>Baſtile.</hi> The ſame ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinary method they practiſed here with us in Q. <hi>Maries</hi> days, when they made uſe of that admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable way of enlightning the Underſtanding with a <hi>Faggot.</hi> And that they are well-wiſhers to the ſame way ſtill, their late attempts upon us have abundantly proved: when, if the mercy of God
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:109098:15"/>had not fruſtated their Cruelty, they would have tried how our Nation might have been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the deſtruction of it. But this we are ſure of, our Lord never practiſed nor approved this ſevere way of proceeding. For when his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples were in a tranſport of zeal, and the two ſons of Thunder would have been ſons of Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning too, and would have called down fire to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> he cools their flame by a mild reproof, ſaying,<note place="margin">Luke 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.</note> 
               <hi>Ye know not what manner of ſpirit ye are of; for the Son of man is not come to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them.</hi> S. <hi>Peter</hi> too, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives a check for drawing a Sword in defence of his Maſter; when, if ever it be lawful to uſe ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinary weapons, he might have urged it then for the defence of ſo much innocency. S. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo was a great enemy to popular Reformations,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.17.</note> adviſing them to take no other Sword than that of the Spirit, which is the Word of God.</p>
            <p>But here the Enthuſiaſtick Zelot will be catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hold of the Sword of the Spirit, and ſay, why, this is our method; it is onely the Spirit that we plead for: <hi>Take heed therefore that ye be not found fighters againſt God.</hi> We are the men that diſcard Reaſon, knowing that God has rejected the wiſe and prudent, and will reveal his mind to none but the ſimple ones.</p>
            <p>But if theſe men will be laying a claim to any new Revelations, or to ſuch a meaſure of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:109098:16"/>the Spirit as the Apoſtles had, let them but ſhew the Letters of Credence which they did: let them but work Miracles and we will believe. Otherwiſe we muſt not be ſo ſilly, to take all for Gold that Gliſters; nor the Hypocondriack Vapours in ſome mens heads, for the pure In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions of Gods Spirit. We may allow indeed in any ſenſe, that their Speech and Preaching is not with the enticing words of Mans Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; but then let them ſhew them to be (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> did) in the demonſtration of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and of Power.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.4.</note> To prevent therefore theſe pious Frauds (for <hi>Rome</hi> you ſee hath not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſed them all to her ſelf) S. <hi>John</hi> ſays,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>Beloved believe not every ſpirit, but trie the ſpirits whether they are of God; becauſe many falſe ſpirits are gone out into the World.</hi> And this is S. <hi>Pauls</hi> rule which he lays down for our inſtruction, in the firſt place <hi>prove all things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.21.</note> and then <hi>hold faſt that which is good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would not be ſo far miſtaken, as if any thing I have ſaid were injurious to Faith; for I deſire that Reaſon may be no higher than the Hand-maid. Onely I think it no good way to pull her eyes out, as if that would make her ſee the better to follow her Miſtreſs. This I am ſure of, Faith can no where be found but in a reaſonable nature: and therefore there can be no ſuch implacable antipathy, no ſuch
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109098:16"/>irreconcilable jarring between them, as ſome do imagine.<note n="*" place="margin">V. <hi>Culverw.</hi> Light of Nat.</note> Why may they not then ſalute one another <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with the Kiſs of Charity? Why ſhould there be a perpetual feud or ſtrife between Faith and Reaſon, ſeeing they are Brethren? Do they not both ſpring from the ſame Father of Lights? And can the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Love and Unity ſend forth any irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable Streams? No, no, Theſe two great Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries may ſhine together without obſcuring each others Light; for whatſoever appears to be a truly Divine Revelation muſt needs be reaſonable. But I confeſs all arguments are thrown away upon theſe men, whoſe very Opinion makes them incurable and uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. For if we ſpeak reaſon to them, that is the thing which they ſo much diſclaim; and if we do not ſpeak reaſon, that were too diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim it too. But thus much for the ſecond particular, having conſidered the manner of the Apoſtles handling them; and that is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by a way of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I come now in order to the third and laſt, which is, to take notice of the influence that his Diſcourſe had upon his great Auditor; it made him tremble. <hi>For when he reaſoned, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now all that I ſhall collect from this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:109098:17"/>is reducible to theſe two Points:</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, The wonderful efficacy of the preaching of the Word: And</item>
               <item>Secondly, The ſmart reflections that accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany the guilty Conſcience.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, It argues a ſtrange efficacy and power in the Word preached, that like Lightning, it ſhould in a moment, and undiſcernably pierce the moſt intimate parts of the ſoul. Who would not wonder that a poor deſpiſed Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Goſpel, ſhould make one of the Grandees of the World tremble? That a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible Priſoner in his Chain, ſhould ſtrike ſuch a chilneſs into the limbs of his Judge, that the warmth of his Robes could not keep him from ſhaking? But yet ſuch is the efficacy of the Goſpel preached, as that it works wonders upon the moſt obſtinate ſinner, and wakens him into an affrightment out of the deepeſt Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thargy. It is upon this account that the Word hath ſo many various appellations in Scripture, all expreſſing the great powerfulneſs of its ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
            <p>In the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> it is ſtiled <hi>A Rod,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 11.4. Rev. 1.16.</note> and in the Revelations of Saint <hi>John,</hi> it is called <hi>A
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:109098:17"/>Sword;</hi> to intimate, that at ſometimes it will <hi>laſh</hi> and <hi>correct;</hi> and at others, if there be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter need, it will <hi>ſlaſh</hi> and <hi>wound.</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jeremy</hi> compares it both to a Hammer and Fire;<note place="margin">Jer. 23.29.</note> becauſe on ſome occaſions it (like the Hammer) beats in pieces the Flinty Heart: and if the neceſſity be urgent, it can put on the nature of Fire; which melting down all the Scum and Droſs, can make the ſoul run into ſuch a pure Metal, as that ſhe neither fears the Fire nor Touch-ſtone.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.16.</note> S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls it <hi>the ſavour of Life and Death:</hi> which expreſſion doth cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſinuate the ſubtle Energy and powerful working thereof; which can kill as well by a Scent, as by a Wound; as well by a Breath, as by a Blow. And if that of the fourth of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> at the twelfth, was not principally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to our purpoſe, (ſome learned men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding it of the Eternal Son of God,) yet at leaſt we may borrow the words in a ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary notion, and avouch with as much truth as confidence, that the Word of God is quick and powerful, and ſharper than any two-edged Sword; piercing even to the dividing aſunder of Soul and Spirit, and of the Joints and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the Heart. Howſoever we are ſure that <hi>Felix</hi> was an Experiment in this kind; and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:109098:18"/>that the horror in his ſoul, and the trembing in his limbs, did argue the wonderful efficacy of the Word preached. But then</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Effect and Conſequent of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Diſcourſe: <hi>Felix</hi> his trembling doth with as much clearneſs argue the ſmart reflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the guilty Conſcience. S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Diſcourſe of Righteouſneſs and Temperance touched him to the quick, who was highly and notoriouſly guilty of the breach of both: and a preconce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption which he had of Judgment after death, now heightned by the Apoſtles particular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, did make his ſoul ſtartle within him; as if he more thought of being called pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to the Bar as a guilty Priſoner, than ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon the Bench as a powerful Judge. So tender and ſenſible a thing is the Conſcience, that though men endeavour by the frequent Wounds they give it, to bring a certain kind of brawnineſs and toughneſs upon it; yet it always keeps ſome part ſo ſoft and quick of ſenſe, that they can never go Scot-free, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome gripes and twitchings from this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Remembrancer.</p>
            <p>Yet I make no queſtion but the Hot-headed Debauchees of this Age, do reproach <hi>Felix</hi> for his Cowardlineſs of Spirit; and cannot but wonder that a Sermon ſhould raiſe a trembling
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:109098:18"/>in him, when if they had been his Auditors, it would ſooner have raiſed their laughter. What! Shall a ſneaking Black-Coat put ſuch Gentlemen of birth and breeding into an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright? Shall a Diſcourſe of future Judgment ſcare them into their Wits? Shall any one think to reduce them to Sobriety, by telling them they muſt one day be called to a reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? No, no; all this ſhall produce no ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thought, but rather a volley of the dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt Oaths and Blaſphemies, and make them cry out in the Modiſh Language of our Times, <hi>God Damme, What will this Babler ſay?</hi> Why ſhould any one with ſuch a ſerious thing as a Judgment to come, put a Damp upon the Pleaſantneſs, or any Allay into the Gaiety of their Temper and Humour; ſeeing they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim an equal hatred to all Conſideration, and the Awe of any thing; and are reſolved to be guilty of as little Fear as Wit?</p>
            <p>Now all the advice that can be given to them (if they be capable of any) is to lay aſide their levity and trifling frame of Spirit; and to conſider the things of another World with that ſobriety of mind, and ſteddy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſedneſs, as becomes a buſineſs of ſo great a conſequence.</p>
            <p>That ſeemingly odd advice which the Old
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:109098:19"/>
               <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Gentleman gave to his Son, when he was upon a Voyage to the <hi>Indies,</hi> is the onely Inſtruction which I ſhall point out to them: "My Son (ſays he) in the firſt place keep "thy Gravity, and in the next place fear God. Intimating that a man muſt firſt be ſerious be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he can be religious. Howſoever, if they will not do this freely, and of their own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, one ſmart fit of ſickneſs will conſtrain them to it; and the Conſcience being then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened, will croud into their company, and make them cry out with the Unclean Spirit, <hi>What have we to do with thee, art thou come to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment us before our time?</hi> The ſad circumſtances that accompany a Death-bed, will make them ſomewhat ſenſible, though they have been long dead in ſin; and the Scene of their mirth will then be quite altered, being conſcious why they, as well as <hi>Felix,</hi> ſhould fear and tremble. As for us, beloved, let the ſight of ſuch examples produce in us a ſtrict caution, and great abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of them; that we may not contract ſuch a confidence in ſin, as if our Conſciences were ſeared with a hot Iron. Let us uſe our utmoſt endeavours for the keeping of the Soul ſoft and tender: and that muſt be by giving a check to the firſt beginnings of ſin, leſt the Soul by being often deflowred and violated, ſhould
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:109098:19"/>caſt away all ſhame, and her innocence toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>And thus have we concluded our third and laſt particular, which was to conſider the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence which S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Diſcourſe had upon his great Auditor, it made him tremble. <hi>For as he reaſoned, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now all that I have to ſay by way of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, ſhall be in ſhort this: that every man would examine himſelf, what a Proficient he is in thoſe Vertues of Righteouſneſs and Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: for they muſt come under an Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation one day, and it will be a great piece of wiſdom to make up our accompts exactly, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by no wits of ours they may be declined or ſhuffled off. I cannot urge a ſtronger, nor more general motive than this: for who would not tremble with <hi>Felix,</hi> if he once enter into the ſerious thoughts of a Judgment to come? For then every man is to be tried for his life, and an eternity of Bliſs or Woe, doth hang upon the ſentence.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.10.</note> 
               <hi>We muſt all appear</hi> (ſays the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) <hi>before the Judgment Seat of Chriſt.</hi> This <hi>All</hi> is without any exception, the glorious Prince as well as the ſordid Peaſant; and he that ſits upon the Throne, as well as he that grinds at the Mill. Be they Rich or Poor, Noble or Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble; there ſhall be none ſo mean as to eſcape
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:109098:20"/>unregarded: none ſo mighty as to decline the Tribunal. And though we ſtand here at a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming diſtance before our earthly Tribunals, yet when we come to make our perſonal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance at the laſt and great Aſſizes; then all thoſe outward diſtinctions of Pomp and Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur will be declined, and the Emperour and Beggar ſhall both ſtand upon the ſame Level. Not but that there ſhall be a ſtrict reſpect and regard had to the greatneſs of mens perſons and places, ſo far as they have had an influence upon their actions to make them exemplary: and as all their proceedings have been as emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and viſible as their perſons, ſo ſhall they be juſtly rewardable with greater honour, or ſorer puniſhment.<note place="margin">Wiſd. 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>Potentes potenter;</hi> ſays the Wiſe Man; Mighty men that have done amiſs, ſhall be mightily tormented: and for the ſame Reaſon, thoſe that have done well, as mightily rewarded. The Magiſtrate muſt give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, not onely for his own, but in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, for the behaviour of other men. How much he hath encouraged Vertue, and diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced Vice: and whether he hath coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly ſtood up for the defence of Gods Church, by putting all thoſe good Laws in execution which were made for her ſecurity.</p>
            <p>The Clergy too muſt give an account of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:109098:20"/>their Stewardſhip: and they ſhall find either an exceeding weight of Glory, or the greateſt load of miſery. They muſt be examined how their Life and Doctrine have agreed together, and whether they have been cloathed with Righteouſneſs, and waſhed their hands in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence before they compaſſed Gods Altar.</p>
            <p>Yea, all inferiour Orders and Degrees of Men ſhall have a fair and impartial Trial; for every one ſhall receive <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the beſt Copies read it, <hi>the things peculiar to his own body, according to that he hath done, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it he good or bad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O happy! thrice happy we! if the belief of this great Article will but work upon us. If the thoughts of a Judgment to come, and a general Reſurrection will have but the ſame effect and influence that it had upon S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 24.16.</note> that every one of us may exerciſe our ſelves in ſuch a manner, as to keep always a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience void of offence both towards God, and towards men: that we may take care above all things that our own hearts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn us not, and then may we have confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence towards God, that he will in his good time bring us to thoſe regions of bliſs, of which he hath given us ſome guſts and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtes here.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:109098:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Unto which happy ſtar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> God of his infinite mercy bring us, for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake; To whom with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, be aſcribed all Honour, glory, Power, Might, Majeſty, and Dominion, now and for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
